We will now examine how the Local Storage is filled during a session and how it remains available after the session is finished.
Let's have a look at the entries in the section Local Storage.
The first 11 entries beginning with the strange key have been generated by Sencha Cmd.
This key is a prefix to the domain and the JavaScript file, it serves to identify the application.
The JavaScript files are stored in the Local Storage, so that they don't have to be called again when another view needs them as well.
The last four entries are the application specific keys.
We will now go through the application and observe live how the local cache is being filled.
I will enter the application as "Teacher". Please observe the changes on the right.
You see that key "role" has been added and the value for role is "1". The value "1" in this case represents the role "Teacher".
If we go back and enter the app as "Student", the value for role changes to "0".
KQC goes back and selects role "Teacher" again.
KQC signs in with his Google account ...
On the right, you can now see that the value for the key “login” is now set to the email address connected with the Google account.
KQC selects a session.
The result: The values for sessionid, sessionname, keyword and shortName are stored in Local Storage.
KQC goes to Lecturer Questions, selects a question and taps Feedback: -> No entries in Local Storage.
If we close the app the again, none of the data is left, apart from the key/value pair for login.
There is a message informing us that no active user is logged in anymore.