Now that we have finished our use case analysis and know what the user wants to do with the software,
we can derive the domain objects from a use case diagram.
Let's have a look:
What is a Domain Object?
Domain Object is a technical term used in software engineering.
It describes a concept related to the application domain of the future user of a piece of software.
This may sound very abstract. What it means is that you need to become a domain expert in the field of the future users of the software to be able to model the expert world of those users correctly.
Example: If you want to develop a medical support system, let's say an imaging system,
then you have to immerse yourselves into the world of a medical expert,
lern their technical terms, analyze their processes,
and then turn all this information into plans and specifications for software development.
Finally, you need to get the approval of the domain experts.
Is this realistic?
Well, it's absolutely necessary.
You need to put yourselves into the roles of the users, i.e. the domain actors.
This is where software engineering comes in.
If you have a look at Unified Modelling Language (UML) diagrams that you find in the course material (in the videos of Derek Banas or on Wikipedia),
you will get an impression of what software engineering implies.
In case you want to perform application development from beginning to end.
This course can't teach you software engineering.
Software engineering is the subject of an entire academic training taught as computer science, software engineering, web engineering etc.
In this course, however, we will develop a web application and limit ourselves to the frontend.
We don't want to develop the web services, the domain objects;
we want to reuse the services available on the web and access them via their public REST Web APIs.
The web offers a plethora of services that we can use.
Therefore, we only need to learn the techniques the browser expects from us: i.e. Javascript, HTML5, CSS 3, AJAX, JSON and others.
We will rely on the ready-made services that are available to us on the web via REST APIs.
If a REST API is well documented, you will identify the domain objects within the URLs.
A REST API can have a hierarchical structure like the ARSnova app, where you have the domain object session on the first level,
then questions, and then answers to the questions.
or the domain objects (resources) the API makes available are canonically strung together.
Note: Not the resources themselves are transferred, but their representations .
A JSON object, an HTML object, an image, a video, all these are representations of the current state of the original resource on the backend.
If you have done some research on the web, you may have come across the API documentation for the ARSnova backend which is available in German only.
In a minute, we will have a look at it.
If an API documentation exists, it is usually self-explanatory.
Take a look at the Twitter API as an example of a well documented REST API.
You can use that API without knowing at all how the services were implemented.
It is an interface that abstracts completely from the implementation, offered as a Software as a Service.
Now lets have a look at the THM wiki which we as computer scientist implemented
for use in application development within our faculty.
Among other documents, you will find the documentation for the ARSnova API.
Let's have a quick look:
You can have a closer look in your own time at home.
You can sort the table by columns.
In the "Resource" column, we see the domain objects: Session, LecturerQuestion, LecturerQuestionAnswer, InterposedQuestion and Statistics.
While our English is far from perfect and some terms may not be quite correct, at least we have tried to make it available in English.
There are interposed questions, lecture questions, answers and that was it.
Then, we have used different verbs of the web:
PUT, POST, GET and DELETE.
In the third column, you find the URLs for the respective resources.
The results of calling a specific URL are described in the fourth column,
e.g. if you enter the URL /session/ (with the slash), you get a list of all session.
If you enter the URL for session without the slash, you get the current session.
In the next column - "Request encoding" - the data format of the response is given.
The data format is usually application/JSON, sometimes nothing, sometimes a query string that contains the information.
The 7th column lists the response codes related to each HTTP request, limited to some responses on the client side.
In the last column, the preconditions. In case you want to call the URL directly, you have to make sure that you meet the requirements, e.g.
if you have to be authenticated or if there is a valid session ID etc.;
otherwise you will get an error message.
That's it. Study it at rest. While there are certainly better API documentations,
at least this document is the attempt of a student to document an interface implemented by someone else.