Now, let's review homework #2.
The assignment: Reverse engineering the ARSnova REST API based on the use cases described in the ARSnova manual.
That is: Going through all the use cases one by one and trying to indentify the main domain objects or resources,
finding out what HTTP request and the responses.
And of course, the central question: Is the ARSnova API RESTful?
Let's have a look at what went right and what went wrong.
It was my intention to have you study and understand the REST architecture by analyzing a running app
rather than by having you program a simple "Hello World" app.
that tries to implement all REST constraints by writing some lines of code.
As mentioned before, the central question was:
Is ARSnova RESTful?
You can answer this question only if you know all 6 REST constraints
and if have understood a principle thatis at the heart of the Uniform Interface constraint:
HATEOAS
We have discussed this principle extensively in the chapter on REST and you will find all the text sources there to recapitulate.
There, we have defined HATEOAS - Hypermedia as the Engine of Application State - as the central requirement for web development according to Roy Fielding.
In case it is not quite clear yet, I recommend reading the text sources again, if need be for a second time.
Here is an example of an good analysis that goes into quite some detail but misses out on the HATEOAS criterion.
Let's have a closer look:
The analysis shows that the student has extensively studied the constraints of the REST API
all 6 constraints are listed and evaluated,
starting with the client-server constraint right through to the uniform interface constraint.
The analysis is not quite decisive about whether the ARSnova API is restful or not
This doubt is due to the fact that the decisive criterion was not examined.
That is, it doesn't analyze if the representations of the domain objects, i.e. the JSON objects, contain Hyperlinks that refer to a possible next state of the application.
And if you analyzed the JSON objects, you will seen that there are no hyperlinks at all.
The developers didn't consider the HATEOAS principle at all.
Well, it wasn't really necessary because the application didn't require it.
The REST client you'll develop during this course, however, should change its application state according to the HATEOAS principle.
Let's walk through homework #2
As a teacher on iversity, I can view the homework again.
And that's what I will do now.
Here are the questions again.
1. Identify and name the main resources (i.e. the domain objects) of the ARSnova web interface.
2. List the complete URLs/URIs of those main resources.
3. Find the methods that are used on those resources.
That is, find them all, not by chance but by walking through all the uses cases.
with the help of the ARSnova manual.
4. The response codes were easy to identify.
5. The type of representation of the main resources ...
... there were only one or two, text/plain was one of them
However, the text/plain MIME type doesn't correspond to one of the main resources.
Und again the main question:
Is ARSnova RESTful?
Here is the assignment in detail:
To find the right answers to these questions, you need the ARSnova manual. Without the manual, the assignment doesn't make sense.
We are in the lucky position to have such a manual.
das wurde ja auch vor der hausaufgabe deutlich formuliert.
What are the main resources?
The application domain of ARSnova is one that you can easily understand.
because you can assume the role of a domain expert
There are students (the audience) and lecturers (teachers).
Why does the client want such an app?
The aim is to get anonymous feedback from the students
check the students' knowledge levels
be able to adapt the lecture depending on feedback and students' questions etc.
Since you belong to the target group of the app, you shouldn't be overly burdened with the task.
Question 1: Now, what are the main resources?
You have already seen some of them in the table ...
but the table is not complete ...
I counted 7 main resources.
As peer reviewers you have already seen the solutions:
- Session
- Preparation questions
- Lecture questions
- Answers to preparation questions and lecture questions
- Interposed questions (from the audience)
- Feedback
But careful - Feedback doesn't really belong here
There is a discussion task on the iversity platform
Have a look at the discussion to find out why Feedback isn't an HTTP resource
due to the way ARSnova was implemented on the backend.
There is one more resource: - Statistics
Question 2: Once you know the resources, you can easily find the correspondig URIs.
You will notice that there are some cryptical signs at the end of the URIs, an underscore followed by a number
_dc followed by something like a timestamp ...
We have posted a question regarding this "annex" in the respective unit
Is it a cookie, a security token or something else? Have a look.
Question 3: What methods are used?
Answer: GET, POST, PUT and DELETE.
Question 4: What are the positive status codes?
This question leaves out the status codes that refer to server errors on the backend
or errors on the client side, e.g. if the resource doesn't exist (error 404) or if the client is not authenticated.
There are quite a few but I won't mention them here.
Question 5: What is the representation type of the main resources?
Answer: JSON
In Javascript application JSON is the data transfer format of choice, anyway.
Question 6: Is ARSnova RESTful?
No, it isn't. We had already answered that question.
There was some discussion as to whether the statelessness constraint might be violated
because ARSnova uses a cookie - a Java session ID.
The counter-argument is that some sort of authentication and authorisation is necessary
to prevent that anybody can access the app.
Therefore, this cookie is absolutely necessary and it isn't used to manage information about the application state.
The cookie doesn't contain any information about the state of the client.
No information about the client is sent to the server. We just need an authentication frame
that is implemented via the backend Spring framework (which is implemented in Java),
It is a security frame to prevent any malicious attacks.
The application state, however, is not managed on the server side.
Der verstoß istdas nichteinhalten des HATEOAS kriteriums.