Welcome to a review on the chapter on "REST architectural style for mobile web applications"
In the next few videos I will explain what Homework #2 was all about
and why I assigned the Homework the way I did.
There were some problems and questions with that assignment
and therefore I think it is important to dig a bit deeper into REST.
When planning to develop a complex, ambitious web application,
you have to ask yourself if you have the necessary theoretical and practical background to achieve that goal.
At the beginning of this course, I recommended reading the Wikipedia article on "Web Engineering"
to give you some insight into the scope of this academic discipline.
Web Engineering is a continuation of Software Engineering.
Over 40 years ago, 1968, Web Engineering was borne out of the software crisis.
And for over 40 years, we have been developing methods, concepts, processes and development models for developing software.
Web Engineering means, to apply the techniques of software engineering on the Web
or to adapt these techniques to the requirements of the web.
Web Engineering is creative, intellectual and inspiring but it's also very difficult.
The reason for developing software is always a need or a requirement that one hopes to solve by using a software system.
Because of that, we need do a Use Case Analysis before we start developing.
These best practices are summmarized by the term "Use case driven development/design".
Thus, we always have to analyze the use cases and ask ourselves: What does the user want to do with the software.
How can REST help us here?
As an architectural style, REST offers us a uniform interface to address the resources of a web service using HTTP request methods.
In the field of software engineering, these resources are called "domain objects".
Thus, Domain Modelling can be defined as understanding the user and his conceptual world, i.e. his domain and set them in relation to each other.
Using REST and RESTful web services, we get a chance to use services we haven't even implemented and
to combine these services to achieve a result that is more than the sum of the individual services.
When we combining different services to create something new, this is called a Mashup.
Mashups allow us to concentrate on frontend development and to consume the services in the background via a RESTful API.
This option has been around for about 10 to 15 year now:
The website "Programmable Web" (http://) aims to list all existing REST APIs (and other APIs as well) and to make them available.
This site offers the possibility to filter all APIs according to different criteria like protocols, data format etc.
If we select REST as protocol and JSON as data format, we get the following list:
The Twitter REST API is the number one on that list with over 800 Mashups at the time the list was compiled
followed by Flickr, eBay, Yahoo etc.
In the videos that follow, I will go through Homework #2 with you.
And I will show you that it is easier to analyze (reverse engineer) a working REST API in order to understand the concepts and developments implemented in that app.
This will serve as a basis for the development of our own app based on a RESTful API.
Why is REST central in this MOOC?
It allows us to develop complex apps within only a few week.
because we can concentrate on the frontend and use abstract interfaces on the backend.
Therefore, we need to understand the architectural requirements,  i.e. the 6 constraints, of a REST architecture.
Client-Server: We have seen that the web is realized as a Client/Server architecture. In this MOOC, we will build a client, not a server side service.
This client should communicate with the backend in a stateless way.
As many request as possible shall be realized via HTTP GET requests.
because GET commands have no side effects and are cacheable on their way to the resource server.
Uniform interface: We will be using a very easy interface with easy operations.
Layered system: We will use the web as a layered system where request can be answered early and near to the browser.
Code on Demand: This will lead us to techniques like AJAX as the last, but optional constraint as defined by Roy Fielding.
Roy Fielding showed us how the web is supposed to work.
And also how the web app we are about to develop should work.
It's the HATEOAS principle that is at the heart of the uniform interface and that is central to the homework and also to the app:
Hypertext as the Engine of Application State.
You need to understand that your client is a state machine and the options available to a client are represented by hyperlinks within the representations of a resource.
The server doesn't maintain any information about the application state of the client.
But the server does hold information about the state of the resources the client requests.
Cut.