Welcome to a new Chapter:
"SPA - Single Page Application"
In this chapter we will outline the requirements that your app (as the practical part of the final exam) must meet.
First, let us define what a "Single Page Application" is.
A "Single Page Application" is a web application that is loaded once. All other content is injected dynamically into this page (into the DOM) without reloading.
In the past, proprietary plugins like Adobe Flash, Java Applets, or MS Silverlight were used to achieve the same effect.
All these approaches were aimed at imitating the look and feel of a native desktop application in the browser ...
i.e. showing real time behaviour and offering extensive graphics.
When Apple introduced the iPhone in 2007, Flash applications were more and more pushed back.
Flash applications weren't supported on iOS devices because they used too many resources.
Also, Steve Jobs was averse to Flash and other proprietary code on iPhone.
The strategy was to use purely web standards: W3C standards, IETF standards: Javascript
JavaScript Single Page Applications in conjunction with
AJAX, JSON, REST and Web Sockets.
AJAX is JavaScript that doesn't interrupt the JavaScript engine in the browser
Asynchronous means: I don't wait for the result of the server und continue only then ...
but I fetch the result later or I will get notified that something new is available.
JSON is the web developers' answer to the XML format, that was regarded as bulky.
While XML was taught for many years and standardized by the W3C, JSON is more compact and and easier to use with JavaScript.
The demand for more real time applications in the browser - without hacks on the HTTP level - resulted in the HTML5 standard WebSocket.
WebSocket is also a network protocol standard on the level below HTTP, i.e. on the common TCP/IP interface.
Now, what are the requirements for the final exam?
There will be a theorectical part, of course, but for the practical part of the exam:
I have already outlined the requirements before, but let me get more specific here:
If you plan to "go the path of least resistance", you can develop a simple AJAX app
that asynchronously calls the statistics data of ARSnova via the ARSnova REST API and visualizes them nicely using Sencha Touch widgets.
When finished, you need to upload your app to cloudcontrol.com.
It is NOT required to port your app to a native format using Phonegap and place it into the app stores.
Your second option: If you have found a group of like-minded people to build a team
including people with experience in design and people with experience in JavaScript
then you can venture to create a Sencha Touch Single Page mashup app
The goal is to develop a mashup app that uses free public REST APIs to  create somehing completely new or to show it in a new way.
So much for the requirements of a team app.
However, keep in mind that team development is difficult, especially when done "offshore" (online).
Even big companies have problems with managing team development efficiently.
Last but not least:
Here is prove that ARSnova is a single page application:
If you visit the ARSnova project on GitHub (folder arsnova-mobile/src/main/webapp), you will only find one html file.
This HTML file is subsequently filled with content and the DOM is built using AJAX calls.
You remember: One of the REST constraints was reloading code.
These are actually snippets. What we are doing here is exactly what Roy Fielding always wanted:
Code on demand.