In this chapter we will examine the key evolutionary step in web technology:
WebSocket
On the one hand, WebSocket is a W3C standard HTML5 API.
On the other hand, it is a protocol of the IETF, a network protocol.
WebSocket allows web developers to use real time behavior in the browser.
How is this possible?
The WebSocket protocol uses the application-level HTTP in the OSI reference model only to establish a connection.
Once the connection is established, the communication takes place on the transport layer TCP.
That's why WebSocket is also called "TCP for the Web".
In message communication, this model is called full-duplex, i.e. a channel with intercom properties,
bi-directional and asynchronous.
What can be achieved with it?
By using WebSockets, different browsers can communicate with one another.
If browser 2 wants to communicate with browser 1 on a different device – with the server as an intermediary – ,
and if this communication is bi-directional, then browser 1 can also send a response to browser 2 via the server.
The browser communicates with the server bi-directionally.
For the first time, the server can perform a data push, that is, send a request to the browser. This behavior is in sharp contrast to the request-response paradigm on the HTTP level.
How to change from HTTP to WebSocket, what are the pros and cons?
Let's start with HTTP 1.1. The standard that was defined back in 1999 by the W3C and the IETF.
You remember, we discussed this extensively in Web Engineering I.
HTTP 1.1 is based on the transport layer TCP over IP.
The basic paradigm of communication in HTTP 1.1 is: The client sends a request and the server sends a response.
That means, the communication occurs only in one direction. This type of communication is called half-duplex.
To circumvent these restrictions, Web engineers were inventive and tried to emulate real time communication on the HTTP protocol.
They did so by using hacks like "Polling", "Long Polling" (also called "Hanging GET") or "Streaming".
The WebSocket protocol is standardized by the IETF, 2011.
WebSocket is also based on the 4th layer (the transport layer) of the OSI model, TCP over IP.
The WebSocket protocol is frame-based.
The WebSocket protocol allows the server to talk to the browser and push data to it.
Thus, the communication is a two-way communication, i.e. full-duplex and asynchronous.
This is different from how a walkie-talkie works, where the receiver of a message has to wait for an end signal from the sender before he can send his message.
WebSocket communication = Full-duplex dual-channel intercommunication.
WebSockets implement native real-time behavior without the overhead of HTTP request-response header parameters and values.
Let's have a look at the three hacks mentioned before that have been widely used on the HTTP level before WebSockets became available.
The most trivial method is called "Polling".
The browser sends requests to the server at regular intervals and the server always sends a response in return.
If there is no event, the response is empty, i.e there is no payload.
If there is an event, the server sends the event to the browser.
This method binds resources, because connections have to be initiated, kept open and closed again.
In our first implementation of the ARSnova app we also took this approach.
However, we soon abandoned this idea, because it puts too much of a strain on the resources.
Another technique is "Long Polling" which can have two different implementations:
For browsers without AJAX support: Long Polling with iframes,
The client sends a GET request and transmits an iframe segment. The iframe includes a  JavaScript snippet.
If there is an event, the server will send the iframe with JavaScript and the browser will process the script tags.
Once that is done, the client will send the next GET request to the server and transmit the iframe.
If there is no event, the server holds the request open until response information becomes available.
When the information is available, the iframe will be returned  to the browser (with JavaScript).
Long Polling with iframe is a "hanging GET":
The response is delayed until an event occurs. (Translator's note: The advantage is that no empty responses are sent as in traditional polling)
Then, a new connection has to be established.
The connection must be kept open until an event occurs.
Timeouts were introduced so as not to strain the connection capacity of a server beyond measure.
Ajax-compliant browser use the XMLHttpRequest object
and the JSON response is filled with an event …
… as soon as it occurs.
There is also always a delay, because the response to the AJAX call is event-driven.
Here's an overview of the WebSocket protocol:
It starts with an initial handshake between client and server. The client sends a standard GET request to a resource ( symbolized by the orange line in the diagram).
In this case the resource is /chat. The protocol used is HTTP 1.1.
The request header includes two new header parameters:
- Upgrade: (with the value) websocket
- Connection: (with the value) Upgrade
There's also a key that is randomly generated in the client and is used to identify the client.
If a sub-protocol (chat, superchat) is available on the server, this can also be specified in the header.
The version number of the WebSocket protocol used should be included, because different versions are not compatible.
As soon as the server receives the request, a TCP connection is established …
… and the server responds with the status 101 Switching Protocols to indicate that the request can be handled.
The server response contains the same header information as the request:
Ugrade: websocket
Connection: Upgrade
The server generates a unique key by combining the client-side key with a global unique identifier.
The response header also includes information about the sub-protocol the server understands.
Once this information is exchanged between client and server, the message exchange itself takes place purely frame-based.
That means, there is nothing but a payload going from one side to the other.
A chief developer at Google summarized this behavior with the following quote.
(Note: KQC rephrasing quote in German)
If you visit  http://www.websocket.org you can access the WebSocket server via the WS protocol.
The WebSocket protocol uses different URI schemes, WS or WSS where the last mentioned uses TLS (Transport Layer Security)
Currently, only Google Chrome Dev Tools offer an analysis option that supports the WebSocket protocol.
When you visit WebSocket.org, you are greeted with a message that tells you if your browser understands WebSockets.
Today, all modern browsers do.
In the section below, I have logged it using Google Dev Tools.
You can see the handshake, the receipt for the handshake (101 Switching Protocols).
If you analyze the behavior of the ARSnova app in Firefox, you can also see this.
When you start ARSnova, a WebSocket connection is requested.
You will see, that the server responds with the corresponding response code and response phrase, i.e. 101 Switching Protocols.
Here you can see the request header with the header parameters Upgrade and the unique key.