Welcome to our new chapter.
This chapter will be about developing web apps using the Sencha Touch framework.
Let's start with a quick overview and the learning objectives.
First, we have to clarify the difference between a JavaScript framework and a JavaScript library.
While jQuery Mobile represents a JS library, Sencha Touch represents a JS framework.
The are several criteria that differentiate a library from a framework:
1. The procedural criterion
A framework is based on the Inversion of Control pattern or - to put it more colloquially - on the Hollywood Principle of "Don't call us, we'll call you".
Hollywood principle means: Hollywood will call you as a actor, it doesn't make sense to apply.
For your code this means that the control flow is based on the framework.
You will adapt the framework to your purposes and implement the interfaces, but when you call the app, the framework is called.
A library, on the contrary, is more of a toolkit, a collection of building blocks that you can use to build your app, but you are left in control.
The control flow is based on your application. You develop your code using library elements.
2. The structural criterion (that I'd like to point out in this chapter)
The Model-View-Controller (MVC) architecture of the code, also called Separation of Concerns.
The term Separation of Concerns (SoC) was coined in the 1970s by one of the great computer scientist of the last century, Edsger W. Dijkstra.
It resulted from the desire to overcome the software crisis by separating tasks and defining interfaces to avoid monolithic applications.
In a GUI orientated application, we have views in the foreground and in the background the data model. In between both, the programming logic.
This chapter includes several videos that further explain the MVC paradigm.
Let's get to the Sencha Touch App that is the objective of this course.
Using a framework like Sencha Touch makes developing a mobile HTML5 app short and straight.
To get an overview of the features of Sencha Touch, you should study the ST Kitchen Sink app.
Here it is:
The example is a working app, you can open it on a mobile device.
(KQC starts iOS simulator ...)
Have a look at the features of the app and the GUI elements (buttons, sliders, toggles etc.).
In the next video I will show you how to install the resources in the course VM, i.e. the Sencha Touch framework and the Sencha Command tool to create an MVC structure for the project.
I have put together a collection of how-tos and tutorials for you to work through.
Sencha puts special emphasis on providing extensive documentation for their products, especially Sencha Touch.
You will find the API documentation as well as guides and video tutorials on their website (http://docs.sencha.com/touch)
There are also a lot of example implementations and case studies which you can study and from which you can learn.
There is one app I'd like to recommend: "Do I need my umbrella?".
There is a three-part documentation for this app that you can follow to build that app yourself within minutes.
This is how it looks like in a browser.
This app uses a web service to fetch the weather data for a particular location.
This app is also mobile-ready.
(KQC opens app in iOS simulator)
(The app has already been bookmarked on the home screen)
The app uses an HTML5 api called application cache or global storage.
I have set the settings for location and units in the browser once and the app caches that information even after terminating the session.
Sencha also offers a special treat: Visual app development without coding.
With Sencha Architect, Sencha makes it possible to generate code using drag & drop,
that is, to generate the code from a visual mockup of the future app.
I have included some videos that show the functionality of this application. You are encouraged to watch them.
If you want to test this application, you can use the 30-day trial version.
Now, let's get to the homework assignment, the fourth and last in this MOOC before the final exam.
The goal is to prove that you can successfully use the Sencha Touch framework.
For that purpose, you should create a minimalistic app.
and upload it to CloudControl.
Homework #4 is due on March 22, 2014, 23:59 (CET).
The homework will be assessed by peer review.
Here are the 3 requirements for the app:
1. Define and implement three different views.
2. The views must be accessible via the toolbar.
2. Each view uses a different UI component.
It's up to you to decide how much time and effort you want to spend on the contents of the app.
The main purpose of this assignment is to show that you have worked through the tutorials and how-tos and are now ready to tackle the final exam app either alone or in a team.